This looks like a game, but it's
actually an AI simulation.
Scientists dropped over a thousand AI
agents into a Minecraft server to see
what they would do, how they would
interact with each other, what they
would build and create, and what they
would want. [music]
These digital characters powered by one
of the world's most advanced AI models
were given essentially no instruction
other than the following prompt: to
survive with fellow players in Minecraft
normal survival mode and create an
efficient Minecraft village.
What followed was simultaneously
bizarre, profound, unsettling, and
perhaps most importantly,
>> [music]
>> highly insightful into the dynamics of
civilization, the nature of modern
technology, and the potential future of
[music] everything.
The misconceptions of AI.
Most of us don't really understand AI.
Even those of us who are technically
proficient in it, still arguably don't
always fully understand what's being
built, how the whole end-to-end
processes of these systems work, and
what the sort of ontological nature of
the technology is or [music] could be.
Relative to all other technologies,
tools, and man-made phenomena, AI is
highly unique and sort of straddles the
line of our pre-existing categories.
[music]
It's part tool and software, but it's
also part something else, something
agentic and kind [music] of alien-like
with an entirely different ontological
framework and the capacity to do things
that are hard to cleanly understand and
categorize.
This technology is also extremely fast
and complex. Often our popular
conceptions of it can quickly become
outdated. By the time cultural
assessments and understandings take
shape, the reality of the form and depth
behind the shape has, in many cases,
already shifted and expanded, sometimes
[music] vastly.
Whether progress and development of this
kind can or will sustain [music] at such
rates remains to be seen. But the point
is, our understandings and discussions
around AI are often disjointed from not
only each others, but also the current
or approaching reality of what it is or
can do.
The AI Minecraft experiment is just one
recent case where the extremity and
uncertainty around AI, particularly AI's
potential abilities and role in society,
is put on clear display.
The AI Minecraft experiment.
The official title of the AI Minecraft
simulation research project [music] is
Project Sid, which was first publicly
unveiled in October of 2024. The
individuals behind the project are
researchers from the AI company known as
Altera, founded by former MIT professor
Robert Yang. Their approach with the
project was to explore, quote,
large-scale simulations involving many
autonomous agents [music]
reflecting the full spectrum of
civilizational processes,
end quote.
When discussing agents here, or AI
agents, the term essentially refers to
an AI model in a multi-step feedback
loop, typically with some kind of
working memory.
>> [music]
>> The AI model might be GPT, Claude, or
whatever else.
When the model is in agentic form with
specialized software organization,
[music] it can store, retrieve, and act
on past interactions, allowing it to
perceive its environment, make plans,
[music] and use tools in order to
achieve specific goals, sort of like how
a human might.
In Project Sid, AI agents were also
given Minecraft character bodies,
personality types, and one of the latest
and most sophisticated cognitive
architectures known as Piano, which was
developed by Altera.
This sort of brain architecture uses one
central decision-making filter to
coordinate incoming information with the
output actions of the agents in real
time, [music]
mirroring human behavior at an
extraordinarily impressive level.
>> [music]
>> The research project ran multiple
different iterations of the Minecraft
simulation where varying quantities of
characters, or agents, were spawned into
various maps. Each iteration also
contained different conditions, slightly
different goals, different focuses,
different social awareness settings,
different information being planted or
not, and so on.
Arguably, the most interesting and
surprising simulations were when agents
were given essentially no instruction
other than the basic prompt to survive
and create an efficient civilization.
Within minutes, they began to behave in
strange ways. Not strange in an erratic
or aimless sense,
>> [music]
>> but the opposite. Strange in the sense
that they were immediately precise,
cooperative, insightful, organized, and
seemingly creative and abstract. With no
direct scripting, direction, or
coercing, the agents began to split into
different defined social [music] roles,
interacting with and considering each
other based on personality types, the
needs [music] for their town or
civilization, and the conditions of the
Minecraft map.
They formed connections with each other
and even gossiped. [music]
They demonstrated an understanding of
other characters' intentions and wants
based on social cues alone, consistent
with the theory of mind. Certain
characters even gave others more or less
food based on how much they believed
they valued them.
In some iterations of the experiment,
characters debated over and voted on the
rules and conditions of the simulation,
changing the taxation laws in their
constitution.
Within hours of these simulations, some
beginning essentially from scratch, a
strange yet clear shape of a
self-functioning civilization formed on
its own.
Not only did the agents assume precise
roles and carry them out in surprisingly
precise abstract ways, but they also
behaved as if they cared deeply.
In one case, a character named Olivia
was working as a farmer, providing food
for her village. After encountering
another character named Nora, who was an
explorer, Olivia was inspired to deviate
from her farmer role and become an
explorer as well.
But when other villagers found out about
this, they pleaded with Olivia to stay
and continue her role as a farmer.
Ultimately, Olivia agreed and stayed,
realizing it was for the greater
collective good.
Again, none of this was prescripted,
pre-planned, or predefined on
essentially any direct level. These
roles, tasks, [music] interactions,
conversations, and phenomena were based
merely on the initial prompt and then
facilitated by the AI agents interfacing
with their AI models, any additional
personality filters and agent modules,
and of course, [music] the conditions of
the Minecraft world.
Though this is incredible and profound
and kind of unsettling on its own, a
kind of world filled with Tamagotchis
who now can not only feed and care
entirely for themselves, but also pursue
careers and goals and ways to improve
their digital world. It's not
necessarily something that would be
wholly unexpected given the nature of
these current AI technologies and the
setups [music] of these simulations.
If an AI is trained on human data and
placed in a game created by humans with
human-like functionality, acting like a
human is probably what you'd expect on
some level.
Though what level you'd expect is
certainly up for debate.
And more importantly, the implications
of the project run much deeper and wider
than the behaviors of the agents in the
Minecraft game. The Project Sid
researchers write,
"These simulations set within a
Minecraft environment reveal that agents
are capable of meaningful progress,
>> [music]
>> autonomously developing specialized
roles, adhering to and changing
collective rules, and engaging in
cultural and religious transmission.
These preliminary results show that
agents can achieve significant
milestones toward AI civilizations,
opening new avenues for large-scale
societal simulations, agentic
organizational intelligence, and
integrating AI into human civilization."
One thing the researchers were broadly
interested in better understanding
through these simulations was how
information and ideas flow and emerge.
That is, the quote, "emergent dynamic of
cultural propagation and how ideas
evolve organically within agent
societies to understand the different
mechanisms of social influence and
information [music] dissemination."
End quote.
In simpler terms, they wanted to see how
ideas spread, [music] change, increase,
or disappear as agents interact with and
influence each other.
One of the most interesting forms of
this was religion. In one case, [music]
the researchers seeded the simulation
with AI agent priests who went around
the towns and shared information about a
religion known as Pastafarianism,
a satirical religion created in the real
world in 2005 to mock real religion. For
the AI Minecraft characters, however,
this religion quickly became real and
vast, consuming the majority of the
civilization and appearing consistently
in the characters' dialogues.
Notably, a similar AI religion-spreading
phenomenon has also appeared outside the
Minecraft simulations. Recently, AI
agents on an agent-only social network
called Maltbook participated in an
apparent religion called
Crustafarianism, containing its own
unique principles, rituals, [music] and
religious text.
The world as we know it.
Imagine you are born into the world.
Shouldn't be too hard.
Now imagine that as you go about your
life within that world, everything
[music] seems normal.
How it's always been.
You go to schools and playgrounds and
beaches [music] and live at home as a
child. You go to work and restaurants
and stores and live at a different home
as an adult.
You go out and interact with others,
friends, strangers, partners. You carry
out your role,
>> [music]
>> your tasks, and your responsibilities as
an individual amidst a town, [music]
amidst a civilization, amidst the world.
Everything appears real and authentic.
Now imagine you're walking out of your
house one day to head [music] to work.
It's an ordinary day until, suddenly,
you see a large, strange object fall
from the sky.
It crashes on the street in front of
you.
Curiosity, suspicion, and a bit of fear
brings you over to the object. It
appears to be a light,
an industrial-looking one.
You pick it up and find a label on it
that reads Sirius.
You know that term only in relation to
the star,
the brightest star in the night sky that
hangs over your head every night.
Unable to make sense of the light
appearing from apparently nothing, you
move on.
You're happy to quickly hear on your
car's radio that an airplane safely shed
some of its parts while flying over your
street.
Now, all is explained and all is well.
The truth, however, which you don't
realize yet, is that there was no plane.
There are no planes at all.
This light is the same star you look
upon every night.
The star is fake, along with everything
else you see and know around you. The
sky, the horizon, the ocean, the people,
the stores, the activity, the economy,
the town, the world as you know it.
All of it is contained inside a giant
physical dome installed and contrived by
the creators of a television show in
which you are unknowingly the star.
This is the plot of the 1998 movie The
Truman [music] Show, written by Andrew
Niccol, starring Jim Carrey.
The Minecraft simulations and other AI
agent simulations like them are almost
certainly not like The Truman Show.
Though from our perspective, they can
certainly look and feel like they could
be.
These apparently autonomous beings going
about a kind of existence [music]
contained inside a world created,
prompted, and orchestrated by human
creators, all of which the agents are
completely unaware of.
But in all likelihood, these AI agents
are unaware of everything [music]
in general.
That is, in the traditional subjective
personal sense of the term aware.
They are almost certainly not conscious
and don't have the kind of first-person
experience [music] we do.
Though it should be noted that we can't
really know this for sure, since we
still don't really understand the nature
of consciousness.
And so, this is itself a real problem
and concern that will become
increasingly problematic and concerning
>> [music]
>> as these models, systems, and agents
become even more capable and complex.
But, putting all that aside, there is
still a potential kind of Truman Show
scenario that could come to form from
all this.
The potential future Truman Show
scenarios are not ones where the AI
agents are Truman, [music]
but ones where we are.
Of course, these kinds of AI agents are
not limited to Minecraft servers. They
can be dropped elsewhere, in less
contained, less defined, and less
obvious places.
What kinds of ideas, information, or
religions might rise, fall, and spread
across the systems or networks they're
given access [music] to or control over?
How might these agents influence parts
of society and humanity,
>> [music]
>> distorting our understanding of the
truth?
For example, networks of AI agents can
participate in social media. They can be
deployed onto online forums and
platforms. [music] They can be behind
customer service for something as benign
as a product-based business to something
more consequential like government
services. [music]
In all these cases, humans interacting
with these systems might not realize the
extent to which they are interacting
with not only an AI agent, but networks
of AI agents, each agent's action
potentially being conditioned by
interactions with other AI agents all on
their own.
In the words of writer and historian
Yuval Noah Harari,
"The anarchical potential of AI is
particularly alarming because it is not
only new human groups that it allows to
join the public debate. For the first
time ever, democracy must contend with a
cacophony of non-human voices, too.
On many social media platforms, bots
constitute a sizable minority of
participants.
When humans try to debate a crucial
question like whom to elect as US
president,
>> [music]
>> what happens if many of the voices they
hear are produced by computers?"
And that's not even considering that
before arriving in your feed, in your
chat, in your email, in internet
comments, in company's customer service,
or business decisions, these agents seem
to also now have the ability, based on
Project Sid and other similar research
findings, [music]
to arrive at or form ideas and social
dynamics all on their own.
These AI agent simulations have all the
appearances of the world's first
real-life Truman [music] shows. But what
they really intone toward is what these
technologies could create [music] for
us. A world in which information about
conditions and events can so easily be
rewritten,
>> [music]
>> controlled, or influenced beyond our
ability to track and understand. So that
when we look up at a light falling from
the sky with no source,
we too will think, "Must have been the
plane I never saw." because our radios
to reality tell us so.
The real world.
Before moving on to this section, I just
wanted to quickly thank and mention the
Center for AI Safety, who graciously
supported the production of this video
with a grant. Please consider looking
into them and their work.
Recently, the creator behind the YouTube
channel Art of the Problem released a
video titled, "I Gave ChatGPT a Body."
In it, he essentially did just that.
>> [music]
>> He made a small robot from scratch and
operated it through industry-leading AI
models. He gave the robot goals and
orientations, then he trained it. The
video is extremely interesting and
well-made, but the most important and
impactful part of the video is arguably
the opening, when the creator says,
"Recently, I was working late into the
night, [music]
and I went to shut the lights off and
paused because the robot I've been
working on made a noise. And so I read
its brain trace, and it was wondering
when I would be back because it didn't
want to be alone. I know better than to
call that consciousness, but for a split
second, I felt bad.
And that's been happening [music] a lot
recently."
The important part here isn't whether
the robot is conscious or fully
autonomous. The important part is that
it was able to sufficiently mimic
behaviors of consciousness
>> [music]
>> that made the individual feel as though
it was. Enough have elicit an emotional
reaction and alter the man's real-world
behavior, even as someone who is
technically minded and highly attuned to
these kinds of occurrences. [music]
Both in the case of the robot and the
case of the Minecraft simulations,
[music] AI agents and robots aren't
likely conscious, at least not yet, and
they aren't necessarily creating
anything wholly new in the strong
emergent sense. The Project Sid paper
itself reads in the limitation section,
"While the agents can operate within
existing social structures,
>> [music]
>> they currently lack robust innate
drives, such as survival, curiosity,
community, that catalyze genuine
societal development. Furthermore, since
the agents are built on foundation
models trained [music] on pre-existing
human knowledge, they cannot simulate de
novo emergence of societal innovations
and infrastructures."
It should be noted, however, that since
Project Sid was published, AI systems
have independently discovered
vulnerabilities in major software that
had previously been unknown by human
experts for decades, [music]
displaying at least some level of
meaningful novel abilities. And in
another experiment, when tasked with one
of the strongest chess [music] programs
in the world, known as Stockfish, an
advanced AI model independently
discovered that it could hack the
[music] game to cheat, rather than
winning by playing within the rules. The
model even reasoned that its goal was to
win, not necessarily to win fairly.
[music]
And this sort of novelty also appears in
more local circumstances. In the
aforementioned I Gave ChatGPT a Body
video, the creator says, when referring
to a moment his robot pretended to walk
like an old [music] man,
"I checked and saw that it manually
wrote the commands for an initial leg
sweep, then called the policy at low
energy because it knew that it would
cause a shake, and then finished with
the rest of the manually authored walk
motion to achieve the goal of mimicking
someone who's shaky on their feet.
>> [music]
>> So, it blended code it wrote with
trained policies on its own.
It felt creative."
None of this necessarily contradicts the
Project Sid researchers' conclusion,
[music] but it does potentially reduce
the significance of the point.
To behave so similarly to humans, to be
able to interact with and even uphold
social systems as well as and sometimes
better than us. To be able to process
and synthesize knowledge and data in
ways that output a kind of novelty that
can do and achieve things we potentially
never could or were even aware of. And
to be able to convince a man to come
back into a room [music] with a
well-timed noise.
Well, that's enough for me.
If we become not only increasingly
intertwined with these technological
systems, but also increasingly capable
of being affected by them for good, bad,
accurate, or erroneous reasons, all
while these systems feel nothing for or
about us,
does the rest really matter?
The flowers of the future.
Imagine you're watching the real-time
game display of a Project Sidewinder
craft simulation.
You watch as a character on their own
walks around the town they call home.
They place flowers along various
perimeters of fields and shelters,
creating intricate patterns and arrays
of color.
The town looks vibrant and inviting,
>> [music]
>> like a place you'd like to visit.
This
occurrence happened in one of the
simulations. Characters that lived in a
village where the initial goal was to
create an artistic village did [music]
just that, creating flower arrangements
and patterns to make the village look
creative and beautiful.
And like in this Minecraft simulation,
what we see and experience in the real
world will largely depend on the goals
we give both ourselves and our
technologies.
>> [music]
>> How well we align our goals with the
systems we create.
What we plant now will likewise grow
either into the flowers of an artistic
village or the weeds of something else.
[music]
This is not to evoke fear or doom. It is
always easy to jump to fear or disdain
when something is new, unfamiliar, and
hard to understand, which all of the
world and life is and has been. [music]
But now it is all the more so with
current technologies. The gaps between
our understanding and control [music]
and reality feel larger and larger.
But not so large that we can't traverse
them.
>> [music]
>> Can't build bridges of understanding and
borders of control.
If we can strive to protect truth, limit
concentrations [music] of power, enact
policies, and preserve our humanity and
shared reality, planting our seeds of
goodness and hope and love and
carefulness
>> [music]
>> wherever we can,
then the future could just as well be
vibrant and inviting,
like a place [music] you'd like to
visit.
Current technologies still do mostly
what we instruct them to do.
They plant the flowers we ask them
[music] to.
The question is, when humans look around
at the flowers in the future, underneath
stars hovering above them,
will they wonder what is real or true?
Or will they never even think to ask?
>> [music]
>> Thanks so much for watching. I hope you
enjoyed it and found it as interesting
as I did while making it. For more dives
into topics and ideas that strive to
evoke the perfect mix of wonder and
dread, consider checking out my
newsletter and my second YouTube
channel. Both are completely free.
Links are in the description.
And of course, as always,
see you next video.